<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-25T11:47:34+00:00</updated><id>https://anubhavratha.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><entry><title type="html">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part V: Towards future-ready markets</title><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-v-towards-future-ready-markets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part V: Towards future-ready markets"/><published>2025-04-21T17:49:13+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-21T17:49:13+00:00</updated><id>https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-v-towards-future-ready-markets</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-v-towards-future-ready-markets/"><![CDATA[<h4>How to successfully integrate uncertainty and risk faced by renewable projects into electricity markets?</h4> <blockquote>This <strong>five-part</strong> series dives deep into the economics of electricity markets and the role that markets can and must play in the decarbonisation journey. But in reality, do they? And what can be done about it?</blockquote> <blockquote>In this last part, <strong>Towards future ready markets, </strong>let’s explore<strong> </strong>some ideas on adaptations that could be made to electricity markets to transform them into drivers of the clean energy transition. We discuss how such adaptions, supported by a strong regulatory mandate, could help to generate long-run market signals that facilitate fast, large-scale, and sustained growth in renewables.</blockquote> <blockquote>Read previous parts: <a href="/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-1-designed-for-the-past-495df82eb04a">Part I</a>, <a href="/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-2-the-incompleteness-of-lcoe-658c44470cce">Part II</a>, <a href="/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-3-an-elephant-called-risk-2b7b37b4df7e">Part III</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-4-is-the-commodity-wrong-7520ea53fee8">Part IV</a></blockquote> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*sEGJic2cLfGu5Txe"/><figcaption>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@mintchap?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral">Brad Switzer</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral">Unsplash</a></figcaption></figure> <p>In <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-4-is-the-commodity-wrong-7520ea53fee8">Part IV</a>, we discussed how electricity is likely not a <em>commodity </em>in a strict economic sense. While that may lead to the conclusion that it’s provision and transition to renewables is best centrally managed by tightly-regulated, governmental agencies in contrast to the current wave of liberalisation and deregulation, I argue that a middle ground is possible.</p> <p>We discussed that a free-market and a well-designed policy framework which incentivises private and public investment into clean energy must co-exist and cooperate to facilitate the transition. I argued how regulation must be the steward for future generations to ensure the necessary investments are done.</p> <p>In this final part, let’s look at how policy and market design could work together more closely to generate the “<em>correct long-run market signals” </em>for those investments.</p> <p>Let’s break that phrase down.</p> <p><em>Market signals </em>commonly refer to the events or trends resulting from market clearings that trigger (by incentivising or disincentivising) market participants to take any action in the market, e.g., to <em>buy</em> or to <em>sell, </em>by <em>how much</em>, <em>where</em> to offer or bid, etc.</p> <p>Here’s a simple example in the electricity context. A <em>short-run</em> market signal is the occurrence of high prices of electricity, let’s say due to an unplanned outage of a nuclear power plant. This deficit in supply immediately triggers more participants to offer to sell in the next market iteration— which in turn, has the effect of bringing the price down and a stable market equilibrium is reached. Therefore, <em>short-run</em> market signals provide generators and loads incentives to change their decisions today or in the coming week (e.g., when responding to weather conditions, planned grid outages or maintenance, etc.).</p> <p>In contrast, <em>long-run</em> market signals refer to those which guide investment decisions, e.g., <em>when and where </em>to build new power plants or loads such as data centers or storage units, <em>how to dimension</em> such investments, <em>which technology</em> to prefer, and so on. A simple example of a long-run signal is the congestion in the grid connecting, say, two countries, which leads to higher prices in one of them. This incentivises investors to, over time, build new power plants in the country with higher prices. This leads to: (a) increase in social welfare in the long term as consumers in the country pay lower prices, and (b) alleviation of congestion in the grid, thereby deferring the investment costs of upgrading it.</p> <p>A market signal, both short-run and long-run, is <em>correct </em>when it aligns the social welfare goals with the rational, utility-maximising goals of individual market participants. In other words, a correct market signal , when generated by a market clearing mechanism, incentivises participants to act towards improving the efficiency of the market while taking actions towards improving their own profits.</p> <p>Long-run market signals are extremely relevant when it comes to bringing changes in markets in the long term.</p> <p>Pertinent to our discussion, long-run market signals in electricity markets must incentivise rapid and large-scale capacity growth in renewables.</p> <h4>Uncertainty and risk mitigation at the core</h4> <p>Given that and the market deficiencies we’ve discussed so far, several academic and non-academic voices have recently raised the topic of a possible redesign of energy markets necessary for a renewable future.</p> <p>These works have been nicely covered in this <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10049815">article</a>, which addresses the question of how future electricity markets may look like<em>,</em> from a well-rounded socio-techno-economic perspective and provides several interesting recommendations.</p> <p>Of particular relevance to our topic here, is the recommendation that electricity markets should go from the current <em>deterministic</em> market clearing practices towards a more <em>stochastic</em> approach.</p> <p>What does that mean?</p> <p>It means that uncertainty and variability, inherent to the power produced by weather-dependent renewables, is accommodated in the market not via ad hoc patch-fixes as is the current norm, but should instead form a structural element of the price formation process itself. The risk arising from the uncertainty and variability is, therefore, priced into the market clearing process.</p> <p>In the interest of full disclosure, I must clarify that this was also one of the topics I examined during my Ph.D. <a href="https://orbit.dtu.dk/en/publications/market-design-for-integrated-energy-systems-of-the-future">research</a>.</p> <p>For example, this <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.12122">article</a> proposes a multi-commodity and multi-period day-ahead electricity market that not only clears quantities of energy (MWh) to be traded, but also flexibility products, e.g., <em>“contracts”</em> that flexible producers and consumers can enter into to provide response to forecast errors during real-time operation next day.</p> <p>These additional commodities (flexibility products) are priced according to a competitive, <em>spatial price equilibrium framework</em>, i.e., at periods and locations where less flexibility is available, the price of these flexibility products is higher (thereby, sending the correct long run market signals for investment in flexible resources e.g., energy storage) and vice-versa.</p> <p>As an interesting side note, the simulated, simple case study in this work (see <strong>Figure 1 </strong>below) already gave glimpses of price depression in day-ahead markets and simultaneous demand for and high prices expected for flexibility products, which we discussed at length in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-3-an-elephant-called-risk-2b7b37b4df7e">Part III</a>.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/485/1*XR8VQGlhRDHnJSsHApIpfg.png"/><figcaption>Figure 1: Average energy price (above) and total flexibility payments made to control policies (below) in the 24-node electricity system considered in the case study with increasing share of renewable energy in the energy mix, denoted by the percentage of total demand from 10% to 60%. Source: A. Ratha et al., <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.12122"><em>Moving from linear to conic markets for electricity</em></a></figcaption></figure> <h4>Flexibility, not energy, must be the star of the markets</h4> <p>The fact that flexibility products must play a crucial role in the grids with high shares of renewable energy is highlighted in this recent <a href="https://en.energinet.dk/media/aobhuqqk/151124_en_outlook-for-ancillary-services-2024-2040.pdf">report</a> released by the Danish Transmission System Operator (TSO), <em>Energinet.</em> Furthermore, the TSO provides some rather interesting data and insights into the historical and projected procurement quantities and prices of flexibility services purchased by the grid operator (i.e., ancillary services) <a href="https://en.energinet.dk/electricity/balancing-and-ancillary-services/prices-procurement-and-projections/">here</a>.</p> <p>Additionally (yet, perhaps more fundamentally), one must pose the question whether pricing electricity based on marginal (fuel) costs is compatible with a future where the energy system is dominated by renewables which not only have no fuel costs but also no opportunity costs.</p> <blockquote>What is the marginal cost of power production from a wind farm or a solar PV park?</blockquote> <blockquote>Without the fuel used up to produce that unit of energy, could it be a combination of the “cost of capital” and the “cost of supply firming”?</blockquote> <p>Here <em>supply firming</em><strong><em> </em></strong>refers to the operation of flexibility provider, e.g., energy storage unit or demand response aggregator, that’s on standby to step in to produce/consume depending on whether the renewable power producer under-/over-shoots the predicted production.</p> <p><em>While cost of capital is fairly easy to calculate, how does one quantify the cost of firming?</em></p> <p>The answer to the above question could lie in a market redesign.</p> <p><em>Firmed supply bidding </em>into the market is expected to play a key role in a future energy market and enable a market-based discovery<em> </em>for the price of firming. At the same time, this generates correct long-run investment signals for flexibility providers to ensure renewables can <em>“truly replace”</em> the dispatchable fossil-fuel based power producers.</p> <p>This is highly relevant because a world where renewable power producers have not been <em>balance responsible</em>, i.e., they haven’t been required to inject into the grid exactly as much as they had previously bid and were cleared by the market, is already (or will soon be) behind us.</p> <p>Such a change in paradigm is well-supported by firmed supply bidding, since it contributes to internalise the negative externality of uncertainty and variability from renewable energy.</p> <h4>In-market hedging against uncertainty and variability</h4> <p>Incorporating firmed supply bidding into electricity markets could take several forms; three of which I elaborate in the following.</p> <p>One possible adaptation to the energy markets is to enable new flexibility-centric market participants such as wind-solar-storage hybrid power plants, power-to-x hybrid power plants, virtual power plant aggregations, demand response aggregations etc. to bid while expressing their full range of operational feasibility and therefore, their ability to deliver a firm supply.</p> <p>Such hybrid power plants act as a <em>physical hedge</em> against adverse renewable production forecast realisations, while additionally bringing new revenue streams to the renewable projects, as discussed in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-4-is-the-commodity-wrong-7520ea53fee8">Part IV</a>. More importantly, they help alleviate the high price volatility we discussed in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-3-an-elephant-called-risk-2b7b37b4df7e">Part III</a>, thus bringing revenue stability for renewable energy projects. As an immediate effect, one can expect occurrences of negative prices and curtailment to become less frequent, which will be a great booster for profits of renewable energy projects.</p> <p>Another possible incorporation of firmed supply bidding could be the adoption of market clearing algorithms that endogenously consider uncertainty and perform a joint clearing of energy and flexibility, as discussed previously. In such a future market, renewables may be mandated to hold physical trade positions that stack up to a firmed supply delivery across the various jointly-cleared market products.</p> <p>Lastly, without necessitating a complete overhaul of the market clearing algorithm, another manifestation of firmed supply bidding could be through regulation-mandated and location-specific flexibility procurement linked to renewable production bids within the existing market framework. In such a future, renewables are <em>responsible for</em> and <em>are explicitly charged for</em> (preferably in a market-based price discovery framework) firming their production to match their energy market bids. They would be required to participate in flexibility trades (and incur risk payments associated with those), where they take positions based on their confidence on forecast accuracy, i.e., asymmetric positions of over-/under-production estimated by them are matched by the flexibility trades they undertake.</p> <p>Flexibility trades, in such a context, behave similar to a combination of<em> state-price securities or Arrow-Debreu securities </em>of some form<em>, </em>which have been used in the financial markets for a long time as effective risk hedging instruments.</p> <p>This is particularly relevant and has strong foundations in microeconomic theory, since for an energy system dominated by weather-dependent producers, internalising the forecast risk is an essential contributor to reach <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complete_market">completeness</a> of the market.</p> <p>In the long-run, such a market sends signals that eventually penalise the risk payments, i.e., incentivise investments in improved production forecasting methods, which, in turn, improve the overall social welfare.</p> <blockquote>Flexibility and firmed supply bidding aside, I can highly recommend this very recently published <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1364032124009766?via%3Dihub">review article</a> which provides an excellent account of the challenges, recent works, and the open research questions on market redesign and price formation in the new paradigm of energy systems, primarily composed of zero-marginal cost power producers.</blockquote> <p>Now that we have discussed a few possible pathways to enable energy markets to become future-ready (or rather, just <em>“catch up”,</em> because a renewable-dominant energy system is already a reality in several geographies), let’s reflect on the relevance of this topic.</p> <h4>Bitter pills for a healthy future</h4> <p>Recalling the role of markets in steering <em>rational </em>and <em>self-interested </em>actors towards building social utility as discussed in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-1-designed-for-the-past-495df82eb04a">Part I</a>, I feel it necessary to elaborate the other facet of that story here.</p> <p>It is also well-known that markets are typically not great at accounting for long-term risks, i.e., rational and self-interested market participants act while excluding such risks from their decision-making, since the impact of such risks on their current <em>utility </em>is negligible, when considered <em>time discounted</em> over the long term.</p> <p>Adverse impacts of climate change, which poses a long-term socio-economic risk, are often neglected in the decisions made by actors in capitalist markets.</p> <p>Therefore, if energy markets have to facilitate the transition to cleaner energy transition, they have to be designed not only with <em>carrots </em>(financial support) for renewable energy but also have proverbial <em>stick </em>(taxes)<em> </em>for fossil-fuel based energy sources. This could, for example, take the form of a <em>carbon tax</em> which is levied on all goods and services based on the emissions incurred in delivering them. Undoubtedly such a step is bold and has been talked about for several years now and requires a global consensus to be built for it to be effective.</p> <p>However, above all, it requires tremendous courage and conviction from general population — the willingness to sacrifice short-term utility to preserve the long-term health of our planet.</p> <p><em>We must agree and accept as a society that consuming goods and services, that are cheap in monetary terms, but whose bill of the associated carbon emissions is charged forward to the next generations, is not sustainable. Bitter pills and compromises must be swallowed by all of us to ensure a future for our planet.</em></p> <p>How do we put that into play? First comes awareness, and with it comes action. We must make our local leaders and decision-makers accountable for climate change mitigation steps; ensure that our planet’s long-term future must always be a part of the agenda, irrespective of the short-term issues facing us.</p> <p>Ultimately, given that <a href="https://degrowth.info/degrowth">societal de-growth</a> is unpalatable to almost everyone, the only solution we have is faster decarbonisation, driven by a massive upscaling of investment in renewable capacity growth.</p> <p>For that to happen, we have to urgently start treading along one of (or a mix of) the two paths: either we correctly internalise the price of climate change externality in all our economic decisions as individuals and economies, or we welcome regulation that overrides the shortsighted profit-seeking behaviour that is characteristic to actors in market frameworks.</p> <p><em>Call me ruined-by-education, but I would much rather prefer only the first solution.</em></p> <p><em>And I believe with an open and constructive dialogue among all stakeholders involved, we can get there.</em></p> <p><em>We must. We cannot afford not to.</em></p> <p><em>Thank you for making all the way through to the end of this rather long article series. Hope you found it useful, engaging, and informative.</em></p> <p><em>I would love to hear your thoughts, insights, and reflections in the comments.</em></p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=2e2bb42a46d0" width="1" height="1" alt=""/>&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;<a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-v-towards-future-ready-markets-2e2bb42a46d0">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part V: Towards future-ready markets</a> was originally published in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions">Clean Energy for Billions</a> on Medium, where people are continuing the conversation by highlighting and responding to this story.&lt;/p&gt;</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part IV: Is the commodity wrong?</title><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-iv-is-the-commodity-wrong/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part IV: Is the commodity wrong?"/><published>2025-04-20T12:37:57+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-20T12:37:57+00:00</updated><id>https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-iv-is-the-commodity-wrong</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-iv-is-the-commodity-wrong/"><![CDATA[<h4>Is electricity even trade-able? Is undoing decades of liberalisation of the sector the right way forward?</h4> <blockquote>This <strong>five-part</strong> series dives deep into the economics of electricity markets and the role that markets can and must play in the decarbonisation journey. But in reality, do they? And what can be done about it?</blockquote> <blockquote>In this fourth part, <strong>Is the commodity wrong?, </strong>we scrutinise electricity markets under a fundamental microeconomic lens and discuss the suitability of electricity as a true commodity. Given the inadequacies of electricity markets in enabling so, we explore a few avenues (some involving uncomfortable truths) to help renewable projects take off.</blockquote> <blockquote>Read previous parts: <a href="/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-1-designed-for-the-past-495df82eb04a">Part I</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-2-the-incompleteness-of-lcoe-658c44470cce">Part II</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-3-an-elephant-called-risk-2b7b37b4df7e">Part III</a></blockquote> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*z-LpYCk7wlMSpn6b"/><figcaption>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@metelevan?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral">Andrey Metelev</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral">Unsplash</a></figcaption></figure> <p>In <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-2-the-incompleteness-of-lcoe-658c44470cce">Part II</a> and <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-3-an-elephant-called-risk-2b7b37b4df7e">Part III</a> of this series, we looked at the cost and revenue side of renewable energy projects in detail, highlighting the market developments that create roadblocks for successful renewable energy projects. We covered how energy markets are posing more risk than reassurance to project developers, thus acting as detractors rather than drivers for renewable projects.</p> <p>In this fourth part, we will explore the microeconomic theory behind electricity markets in an attempt to seek answers to the above. We will question the very fundamental pillar that upholds energy markets and discuss possible solutions to mitigate their deficiencies.</p> <h4>Is electricity even trade-able?</h4> <p>Given the inadequacies current energy markets exhibit in fulfilling their role in the clean energy transition, Brett Chistophers concludes his book, <em>The Price is Wrong </em>(read <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-1-designed-for-the-past-495df82eb04a">Part I</a> for details), with a radical claim.</p> <p>Brett claims that, in fact, electricity as a <em>commodity</em> is wrong. He refers to (and extends) Karl Polanyi’s argument around <em>fictitious commodities</em> introduced in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Great_Transformation_(book)">The Great Transformation</a>.</p> <p>Brett argues that <em>electricity</em>, in addition to <em>land</em>, <em>labour</em>, and <em>money</em> as identified by Polanyi, is a fictitious commodity. This argument is based on the fact that electricity traded (in its current form of MWh of energy) has been forcefully <em>commoditised </em>to fit the liberalisation and marketisation agenda in the late ’80s and early ’90s. The main propeller behind this agenda being the neoliberal reforms pushed for by economists in financial institutions such as World Bank and International Monetary Fund. Whereas, electricity, in fact, exhibits properties of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necessity_good"><em>necessity good</em></a><em>, </em>one which must be delivered to the public, irrespective of the cost involved, and is therefore, naturally suited to be delivered by tightly-regulated, vertically-integrated suppliers owned by governments.</p> <p>Therefore, Brett concludes that <em>deep</em><strong><em> </em></strong>and<strong><em> </em></strong><em>ongoing</em> financial involvement by governments in the energy sector around the world is the only way to decarbonise it at the scale and pace necessary to mitigate climate change.</p> <p>The way I read this conclusion is that it leaves two viable options on the table: either (i) ramping up of the subsidies and other support mechanisms for renewables (i.e., <em>deliberately and continually overriding the free market dynamics</em>), or (ii) a complete overthrow of the current liberalised energy markets by nationalised, vertically-integrated utilities.</p> <p>Interestingly, there are some merits to both these options. For the first option, if not for any reason other than the fact that the classical competitors of renewables, i.e., fossil-fuels, have typically enjoyed (and still do) decades of direct and indirect state subsidies around the world. <em>So why shouldn’t the same courtesy be extended to renewables?</em></p> <p>To justify the second option, one need only consider the reality of how electricity markets truly work in practice. To trade electricity effectively, we must have an intricate and complex structure of regulations governing a multi-layered market structure (involving a combination of <em>futures, spot, balancing, </em>and<em> capacity </em>markets) in place.</p> <p>Looking at such complexity, it would be naive to not question whether all this orchestration reflects our futile attempts to tame an untameable beast.</p> <p>Ensuring a safe and reliable supply in a complex, interconnected physical system, which <em>does not obey any human-enforced laws for fulfilment of transactions and where physical laws govern the instantaneous flow of the commodity (electricity), </em>raises credible questions of whether we are asking too much of the electricity markets.</p> <p>That is, irrespective of any shape or form of the market orchestration itself, is it the commodity that is indeed <em>wrong</em>?</p> <blockquote>One must ask, where does that lead us?</blockquote> <blockquote>Is re-nationalisation of our energy system and perennial government subsidies the only way forward to save the warming planet?</blockquote> <blockquote>On the other hand, the industry has expended (and is still expending) massive amounts of resources since the 1990s to prop up a mostly-functional system to organise market-based energy transactions.</blockquote> <blockquote>Is it time to pull the plug on it?</blockquote> <p><strong><em>Not necessarily, at least, in my opinion.</em></strong></p> <p>I believe, there is a middle ground where free-market capitalism and calls for more regulation <em>can and must</em> co-exist (and <em>cooperate</em>) to make energy markets fit for the purpose of accelerating clean energy transition.</p> <h4>From cost reduction towards value certainty</h4> <p><em>First</em>, there must be a fundamental rethinking about what does it take for renewable energy projects to take off the ground in a market-based environment. With that comes the need to assess and communicate the <em>true-cost </em>of a failed renewable energy project.</p> <p>Let me clarify.</p> <p>Hopefully by now in this article series, I have convinced you that profit (and the perceived certainty of it) governs the growth of renewable energy projects, not the low costs of renewables.</p> <p>From an individual project perspective, therefore, we must get rid of the current thought process around <em>“cost of energy”. </em>While analysing financial feasibility of projects, LCOE must be replaced by a metric that represents the <em>“cost of energy delivery”</em>. We need to leave behind the zealous excitement over the <em>cost-competitiveness at point of generation </em>to adopt a more pragmatic and self-reflective view that focuses on ensuring <em>value-competitiveness at the point of consumption </em>instead.</p> <p><em>This implies looking beyond the sheer number of MWh produced, rather focusing on the value that each MWh produced brings at a low risk.</em></p> <p>This could, for instance, be achieved by extending the conventional revenue streams available to renewable projects (i.e., <em>participation in volatile energy markets or low PPA price lock-in</em>) to provide grid services and adding behind-the-meter assets.</p> <p>This strengthens the revenue prospects significantly, as renewable energy projects are no longer passive, non-dispatchable <em>price-takers </em>in the market. Rather, they earn additional revenues as <em>active</em>, <em>flexible</em> market participants who actively contribute towards strengthening the electricity grid.</p> <p><strong>Figure 1 </strong>below illustrates a few examples and lists the pros and cons of such value-based de-risking pathways for the development (augmentation) of new (existing) renewable energy projects. As evident from this list, achieving a successful value competitiveness of renewables is a multi-faceted challenge which needs a similar response to address it.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*xAkXboCW8RleaM5SO655yg.png"/><figcaption>Figure 1: Example of two de-risking pathways available to renewable energy projects, each with their pros and cons. Source: Author’s own illustration.</figcaption></figure> <p>Another critical pathway to increase value competitiveness of renewable energy projects is through <em>energy trading</em>. Energy trading is expected to play a key role, given the headwinds faced by renewable energy projects due to the various geopolitical and regulatory bottlenecks we have discussed in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-1-designed-for-the-past-495df82eb04a">Part I</a> and a shift away from long-term PPAs (refer <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-3-an-elephant-called-risk-2b7b37b4df7e">Part III</a>).</p> <p>Short-term energy trading, both asset-oriented energy balancing and profit-oriented <a href="https://www.statkraft.com/newsroom/explained/trading-statkraft-a-major-player-in-the-power-market/">proprietary</a> kinds, can become effective mechanisms to maximise and stabilise operational revenue from energy assets and provide confidence to potential investors on the value of supporting new and operational renewable energy projects.</p> <p>This could be achieved by, e.g., revenue stacking across markets and products, adopting risk-adaptive trading strategies built upon a foundational understanding of energy markets, and making robust data-driven decisions considering uncertainty and risk.</p> <p>It is, therefore, exciting to see so much innovation happening in this sphere, spearheaded by startups and small companies, see <a href="https://www.f6s.com/companies/energy-trading/mo">here</a> for an example list.</p> <p>Hopefully, short-term trading will eventually achieve its full potential in de-risking renewable energy projects, beyond price arbitrage and liquidity provision, to support the clean energy transition.</p> <h4>What is the cost of energy system transition, really?</h4> <p>Zooming out from individual projects and adopting a systemic perspective, it is crucial that energy academicians and practitioners weave a public narrative that acknowledges and publicly admits the challenges that a renewable-based energy system entails.</p> <p>Some of these challenges, I have discussed in this series, e.g.,<em> ensuring adequacy of available energy, controllability of generation for a continuous supply-demand balance, and above all, the requirement of a massive, expensive build-up/upgrade of grid infrastructure, supported by short- and long-term energy storage, to deliver clean energy to consumers all year round. </em>This recent IEA <a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/integrating-solar-and-wind">report</a> further highlights these challenges, dividing them into 6 phases of integration of weather-dependent renewables. <em>(See </em><a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/integrating-solar-and-wind/infographic-six-phases-of-variable-renewables-integration"><em>infographic</em></a><em>)</em></p> <p>However difficult it may be, we must foster a constructive dialogue that convinces decision-makers and more importantly, the general public to whom they’re answerable, that these are existential challenges that we must overcome by making <em>massive meticulous strategic investments in R&amp;D,</em><strong><em> </em></strong><em>public infrastructure projects</em>, and<em> targeted financial support aimed at climate change mitigation.</em></p> <p>Because, contrary to popular belief, doing so makes economic sense right now.</p> <p>And the cost is not just about the cost of renewables, rather the cost of not investing.</p> <p>Not in the short- or long-term, but in the now!</p> <p>And it is less relevant a question what form this targeted and country-specific investment (and the regulatory framework underlying it) takes.</p> <p><em>Needless to say, it does matter whether this support takes the form of direct or indirect capital subsidies (e.g., in the US and the UK), an extension of feed-in tariffs (e.g., in China and Germany), double-sided contract for differences or CfDs to hedge market price risk (e.g., in the UK and soon in DK), socialisation of grid costs (e.g., in the Nordic countries), preferential treatment while integrating renewables to grid (e.g., in Spain), favourable land leases for large-scale renewable projects (e.g., in India and China), research grants to academia and industry for CleanTech breakthroughs, and so on.</em></p> <p>The investment mechanisms must be designed to fit the specific needs of individual countries and regions. But the fact that we need this investment must no longer be debated. We have so many investment models that have worked already to support renewables, and we must keep iterating on them to make them even better.</p> <p>As a more concrete example, one model could be executed by designing incentives for large electricity consumers, e.g., metal and steel industries, data centers, etc. to procure their energy demand from renewable energy projects through (long-term) corporate PPAs, as hinted in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-1-designed-for-the-past-495df82eb04a">Part I</a>.</p> <p>Such a policy framework when implemented with a requirement for “<em>additionality” — </em>i.e., demand must be met with new (greenfield) energy projects, will give a massive impetus to de-risking renewable energy projects. This has recently been the case, when massive industrial off-takers with long-term PPAs have repeatedly saved the day for renewable projects. For instance, in case of the <a href="https://group.vattenfall.com/press-and-media/pressreleases/2025/vattenfall-builds-germanys-largest-offshore-wind-farm">Nordlicht wind farm</a> project in Germany, the recent agreement with the chemical giant BASF on a long-term PPA was crucial for the final investment decision to be reached.</p> <h4>Regulation: Voice of the future generation</h4> <p>In their recent article titled, <a href="https://academic.oup.com/icc/article/32/2/277/7043810"><em>Climate change and growth</em></a>, eminent economists and thinkers <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Stern,_Baron_Stern_of_Brentford">Nicholas Stern</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Stiglitz">Joseph Stiglitz</a> argue that at this juncture, the opportunity costs of taking strong climate actions are especially low whereas the benefits are incredibly high. In other words, it makes macroeconomic sense to <em>invest heavily</em> in climate change mitigation now and that conventional metric of achieving <em>economic growth </em>is in complete alignment with these investment costs.</p> <p><em>This is where regulation must step up in its role as a steward of the future generations.</em></p> <p><em>Where corporate boardrooms see a horizon of a few years, at best, for return on capital deployed, regulators and governments must work relentlessly and ruthlessly to force a longer view on both public and private investments.</em></p> <blockquote>Once we’ve rid the air of the grandiosity of renewables and acknowledge that they come with their flaws that we must address by public and private investments, how do we adapt current energy markets to transform them to become drivers of the clean energy transition rather than detractors?</blockquote> <blockquote>This question is explored in the last part of this article series, “Part V: Towards future-ready markets”.</blockquote> <p><a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-v-towards-future-ready-markets-2e2bb42a46d0">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part V: Towards future-ready markets</a></p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=7520ea53fee8" width="1" height="1" alt=""/>&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;<a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-4-is-the-commodity-wrong-7520ea53fee8">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part IV: Is the commodity wrong?</a> was originally published in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions">Clean Energy for Billions</a> on Medium, where people are continuing the conversation by highlighting and responding to this story.&lt;/p&gt;</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part III: An elephant called Risk</title><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-iii-an-elephant-called-risk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part III: An elephant called Risk"/><published>2025-04-18T11:27:51+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-18T11:27:51+00:00</updated><id>https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-iii-an-elephant-called-risk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-iii-an-elephant-called-risk/"><![CDATA[<h4>How do financial institutions look at renewable energy projects from a risk perspective? And how is this perception evolving?</h4> <blockquote>This <strong>five-part</strong> series dives deep into the economics of electricity markets and the role that markets can and must play in the decarbonisation journey. But in reality, do they? And what can be done about it?</blockquote> <blockquote>In this third part, <strong>An elephant called Risk, </strong>we dive deep into the risks associated with the revenue streams typically renewable energy projects rely on to reach profitability. We explore a few key market developments that are increasing the risk perception of such projects.</blockquote> <blockquote>Read previous parts: <a href="/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-1-designed-for-the-past-495df82eb04a">Part I</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-2-the-incompleteness-of-lcoe-658c44470cce">Part II</a></blockquote> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*HAPiCrGXo3ahMfNd"/><figcaption>AI-generated image representing the proverbial elephant in the room called RISK, drawn using inspiration from the surrealism style. [Generated using ChatGPT from OpenAI on 29.03.2025]</figcaption></figure> <p>After having looked at the costs in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-2-the-incompleteness-of-lcoe-658c44470cce">Part II</a>, let’s change our perspective now to look at the revenue side for the economics of renewable energy projects, more specifically, at the risk perception associated with those revenues.</p> <p>Besides project costs and the delays in project execution potentially exacerbating those, a key determinant of the whether an investment decision regarding a project is successful is how stable the foreseen revenues are.</p> <p>To illustrate, let’s do some roleplaying, shall we?</p> <h4>So…tell me, how do you plan to make money?</h4> <p>Imagine yourself walking into a bank seeking a loan.</p> <blockquote>You: “I would like to borrow a million euros for my favourite project.”</blockquote> <blockquote>Bank: “How wonderful! We are here for you, exactly for that. We would love to lend you the money. But first, may we know how you intend to pay us back?”</blockquote> <blockquote>You: “That’s great to hear, thank you. So…about paying back, I know that I “should be” able to earn money for the hours I work. But which hours I can work, in reality, depends on the weather; therefore, that is beyond my control. All I can tell you is that for any given hour in a year, there is a one-third probability that I would be able to focus on working.”</blockquote> <blockquote>Bank: “I see. So you will be able to earn money for 33% of the year’s working hours?”</blockquote> <blockquote>You: “Ah, I wish that were so…but not really. If the conditions are really great for me to work, then, unfortunately I get paid much less in each hour that I work. Sometimes, I might even have to pay to work under such conditions. So it might be worthwhile in those periods to not work at all, so I can rest well to work in other periods.”</blockquote> <blockquote>Bank: 😮</blockquote> <p>While the above interaction may sound oversimplified, unreal, and downright comical to many, it is unfortunately the meta-conversation in reality when renewable project developers approach financial institutions to raise capital.</p> <p>To understand why, let’s break the conversation down.</p> <p><em>First</em>, naturally being weather-dependent, renewable energy sources, such as solar PV and wind, produce energy only when the sun shines or the wind blows.</p> <p>This is measured by a generic, unit-less metric called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capacity_factor"><em>capacity factor </em></a>of a power plant which is the ratio of the actual electrical energy (MWh) generated to the total possible generation (MWh), given the size of the power plant in a given year. Typical values of capacity factors for renewable energy sources depend on site-specific conditions (e.g., how many hours of sunshine it receives, what is average wind speed, etc.) as well as the free transmission line capacity available to off-take the energy generated to sites of consumption. The number 33% mentioned above is just an <a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/1498992/capacity-factor-renewables-by-technology/">example</a>, but is not far-fetched for many sites.</p> <p><em>Second</em>, in a given market, as the share of renewable energy grows, there’s an effect called p<em>rice cannibalisation</em> that comes into play. This implies that as more renewables enter the market, the average price they receive in the market per unit of energy (MWh) produced by them reduces, i.e., <em>renewable projects eat into their own profits</em>. This is because renewables participate in energy markets offering their forecasted energy production at a zero price, since the are no fuel costs associated with actually producing that energy and there is no opportunity cost with not being asked to produce (i.e., when their bid gets rejected by the market).</p> <blockquote>If you would like to better understand the concept of price cannibalisation and more generally, the price formation dynamics in electricity markets, feel free to check out this short write-up, <strong>Price cannibalisation effect:</strong></blockquote> <p><a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/price-cannibalisation-effect-a09f4ed371e6">Price cannibalisation effect</a></p> <p><em>Lastly</em>, not just the depression of average prices which reduces the expected revenues generated by renewable projects, it’s the variability of those prices (and consequently, the revenue) that especially troubles financial institutions.</p> <h4>A rollercoaster ride into uncertainty</h4> <p><strong>Figure 1 </strong>below, sourced from a <a href="https://vbn.aau.dk/ws/files/565162718/P10_final.pdf">M.Sc. thesis report</a> with author’s permission, shows the trends in hourly day-ahead electricity prices in one of the energy market regions in Denmark (DK2), which is surrounded by market zones typically having high share of renewable energy in the electricity mix. It’s hard to miss the recent intense increase in volatility of day-ahead prices in electricity markets. This can be explained by Russian invasion of Ukraine in the beginning of 2022 led to sudden disruption of natural gas supply chain in Europe leading to price increases that shook Europe.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*q2xSVYqq_dXzfDLXcEpBTw.png"/><figcaption>Figure 1: Day-ahead electricity prices in DK2 region in Denmark in hours 8, 16, and 24 from Jan 2015 to Sep 2023. (Re-used with author’s permission) Source: <a href="https://vbn.aau.dk/ws/files/565162718/P10_final.pdf">“Analysis of day-ahead prices and influencing factors in the Nordic power market”</a>, M.Sc. Thesis by Anders Linnemann Nielsen, Aalborg University, 2023.</figcaption></figure> <p>While some level of price stabilisation has been achieved since then as the supply chains have adjusted in response to the shock, price volatility still remains quite high, as observed in this very recent <a href="https://www.acer.europa.eu/sites/default/files/documents/Publications/2025_ACER_Gas_Electricity_Key_Developments.pdf">report</a> on the electricity and gas market developments in Europe produced by the EU Agency for the Cooperation of Energy Regulators, ACER.</p> <p><strong>Figure 2 </strong>below,<strong> </strong>sourced from the same report highlights the seriousness of this development by showing the share of days in the recent years when the day-ahead electricity prices in the hours of the day varied larger than 50 EUR/MWh. To put this number into perspective, consider that the average wholesale electricity price itself was less than 50 EUR/MWh up until early 2021 in most European energy exchanges, see <a href="https://aleasoft.com/european-electricity-markets-reached-highest-prices-since-at-least-2019-may/">here</a>.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*2DkZ2GPuetUmO1bwlIhnJw.png"/><figcaption>Figure 2: Share of days in a year when prices in day-ahead electricity markets in EU swung more than 50 EUR/MWh within the single day. Data source: <a href="https://www.acer.europa.eu/monitoring/MMR/electricity_gas_key_developments_2025">ACER Market Monitoring Report 2025</a>.</figcaption></figure> <p>Volatility in electricity market prices is expected to increase as more renewables become a part of the generation mix. In fact, it will be structural and fundamental to the electricity markets in the near-term. This can be partly explained, adopting some simplifications, by recalling the price formation process discussed in the example in the write-up on <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/price-cannibalisation-effect-a09f4ed371e6"><em>price cannibalisation effect</em></a><em>, </em>as illustrated in the following. Other factors include the increasing coupling among the markets, the lagging growth of flexibility providers in the system compared to the growing share of renewables, etc. <em>(A detailed analysis on electricity market volatility will be the topic of a future article!)</em></p> <p>In the hours when sun shines and the wind blows, prices will be very low — in fact, hours with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/duncan-steen-97434453_weve-shared-some-insight-on-european-negative-activity-7289581425886990336-NvVh?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;rcm=ACoAAAIwpbQBAR81qBQmgL4YxitSkVbkYni4oX8"><em>negative prices</em></a> are growing year-on-year particularly during sunny midday hours as supply massively overshoots demand. Whereas in hours with reduced availability of these resources, prices shoot up as fossil-fuel based generators (mostly gas-fired power plants) with high fuel costs have to ramp up their production to meet the demand. Moreover, as the grid becomes “cleaner”, the capacity factor for these generators reduces, which coupled with increasing gas prices, implies that they must bid at very high prices to maintain the same level of returns on investment promised to the asset owner(s).</p> <p>As a result, electricity prices often swing wildly between very low and very high and become highly correlated with weather — which is notoriously difficult to predict accurately. Not to mention the extended periods of windless, cloudy days and nights — so-called periods of <strong><em>“Dunkelflaute” </em></strong>in German, which loosely translates to “<em>dark-lull” — </em>when reliance on expensive sources of energy becomes critical, given the current absence of long-term electricity storage options.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*WMX-B-8CdzV44f4E"/><figcaption>Figure 3: AI-generated image representing the Dunkelflaute (dark-lull) conditions in post-impressionist style, drawing heavy inspirations from Van Gogh’s classic, Starry Night. On such nights, non-renewable generating sources must typically be ramped up, irrespective of their climate footprint, to meet the electricity demand. [Generated using ChatGPT from OpenAI on 29.03.2025]</figcaption></figure> <p>Due to such price dynamics, the risk associated with uncertain revenues — termed as <em>merchant market risk, </em>looms large over renewable projects.</p> <p>Even typical PPAs written by electricity retailers (utility companies, for instance) to off-take the electricity from such projects are often a lagging indicator of this risk, i.e., they are <em>marked-to-market. </em>This implies that there is always some an exposure to wholesale electricity market prices of various degrees associated with such contracts.</p> <p>Moreover, the underlying contract duration is trending towards the shorter end over the years to reflect the fast-changing trends in average prices — <em>no utility wants to be locked-in for 10 years at a price of 60 $/MWh when forecasts put at least some probability mass on average market prices lingering around 42 $/MWh in 3 years time.</em></p> <blockquote>Current geopolitical conflicts around the world further exacerbate the risk woes of renewable projects. Financial support from states and political stability among countries appears shaky as the priority and focus of governments shifts from long-term climate change mitigation to short-term adaptations to the changing world order.</blockquote> <p><em>Do all of the above imply that buying and selling electricity will always be “risky business” going forward?</em></p> <p><em>How does one reconcile this with the fact that electricity demand is projected to (and most likely will) increase significantly in all countries around the world?</em></p> <p><em>If this were any other commodity, long-term contracts should ideally be the mechanism by which resellers should be looking to lock-in favourable prices at a time when global (and local) demand to hedge the long-term price risk.</em></p> <p><em>Why is it not the same for energy? Is there something more fundamental at play here?</em></p> <blockquote>Let’s explore these questions in depth in the next part of this article series, “Part IV: Is the commodity wrong?”</blockquote> <p><a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-4-is-the-commodity-wrong-7520ea53fee8">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part IV: Is the commodity wrong?</a></p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=2b7b37b4df7e" width="1" height="1" alt=""/>&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;<a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-3-an-elephant-called-risk-2b7b37b4df7e">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part III: An elephant called Risk</a> was originally published in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions">Clean Energy for Billions</a> on Medium, where people are continuing the conversation by highlighting and responding to this story.&lt;/p&gt;</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Price cannibalisation effect</title><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/price-cannibalisation-effect/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Price cannibalisation effect"/><published>2025-04-18T09:53:27+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-18T09:53:27+00:00</updated><id>https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/price-cannibalisation-effect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/price-cannibalisation-effect/"><![CDATA[<h4>An oversupply of renewable generation leads to new projects eating into the profits of existing ones, hence the term cannibalisation. But why does it occur?</h4> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*CdBw8eEBAU4sUV3Q"/><figcaption>AI-generated image, generated using ChatGPT from OpenAI on 29.03.2025</figcaption></figure> <p>Recently, the term <em>price cannibalisation</em> has been cropping up in the public discourse around the energy system transition, addressed by a variety of viewpoints and interests. For instance, some argue that it brings high investment risk for renewable projects, e.g., <a href="https://www.leadingedgeenergy.com.au/blog/electricity-price-cannibalisation-oversupply-drives-down-prices/">here</a>, whereas others downplay it by highlighting that those fears maybe exaggerated, e.g., <a href="https://www.energymonitor.ai/policy/market-design/why-reports-of-renewables-price-cannibalisation-may-be-greatly-exaggerated/?cf-view">here</a>.</p> <p>Regardless of the viewpoints, it is important for the general audience to understand the mechanics behind this effect, which is the purpose of this short write-up.</p> <p>While this <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0140988319303470">paper</a> (available Open Access) provides an academic treatise of the nuances involved considering the case of California, in the following, I explain the effect using an illustrative example of a day-ahead electricity market clearing.</p> <p>Day-ahead electricity markets are where most of the volume of electricity is traded currently and they operate on the principle of <em>marginal pricing. </em>This implies that the marginal cost (€/MWh) of the marginal generator (the most expensive generator that needs to be run to fulfil the ‘<em>marginal demand</em>’ or the last MWh of demand) in a given period (e.g., hour, in case of the hourly day-ahead markets) is the <em>price of electricity </em>in that hour.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*4lwuu5Sn3y22q_x_5zn8Dw.png"/></figure> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*heL2-V-gEjbmX-I4e-nuzg.png"/><figcaption>Figure 1: An illustration of the price formation process underlying day-ahead electricity markets. Source: Author’s own illustration.</figcaption></figure> <p>In the above example, if the demand at a given hour were 240 MWh, the market clears with marginal generator as <em>G2</em> and therefore, it’s marginal cost (fuel cost of 15 €/MWh in the case of the fossil-fuel based generator shown) is the price of electricity. This price, is in fact, received by <strong><em>all</em></strong> producing generators, i.e., Generator <em>G1</em> receives a revenue of 100 × 15 = €1500 at a production cost of 100 × 10 = €1000, making a neat profit of €500. Whereas the marginal generator collects a revenue of 140 × 15 = €2100 at break-even.</p> <p>Now imagine that this is an hour in a cloudless sunny day around midday and that solar PV producers <em>G4</em> and <em>G5</em> (not shown in Figure 1, each with 100 MW capacity each and producing at full capacity) are also bidding into the market at their marginal (read, <em>fuel</em>) cost of 0 €/MWh.</p> <p>This shifts the entire offer curve (merit-order curve) to the right, therefore, the new market price is set by <em>G1</em> which is now the marginal generator and the price received by the producers is now 10 €/MWh. This is neat for solar PV producers, since they get paid €1000 each at no cost of production.</p> <p>Sounds great, right? And it is indeed! This profit represents a <em>market signal</em>, which is supposed to work towards incentivising more solar project developers to build and operate solar PV plants in the region.</p> <p>Now, imagine the electricity demand remains fixed at 240 MWh and a sixth solar PV producer <em>G6</em> with a capacity of 50 MW joins the generation pool. Suddenly, one of the solar PV producers becomes the marginal generator and as a result, the price is set to 0 €/MWh and no producer makes any money in that hour in the market.</p> <p>The above illustrates the price cannibalisation effect in action for a given hour of the year. The entry of the third renewable producer in the region eats into the profits of all producers, hence the vivid cover image of this article, depicting renewables devouring themselves.</p> <p>As the overall generation pool shifts more towards such zero-marginal cost producers, more hours with zero (or very low) or even negative prices occur (particularly during high solar production hours), which reduces the average price that can be received by new projects willing to enter the market. This, in turn, adversely affects the revenues that market participating projects can make and therefore, diminishes the interest of investors and bankers in such projects.</p> <p><em>For more curious readers, I can highly recommend </em><a href="https://www.epexspot.com/en/basicspowermarket"><em>this</em></a><em> fantastic resource on the basics of electricity market and price formation process, including a special focus on the intriguing case of negative prices published by EPEX SPOT, a market operator in Europe.</em></p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=a09f4ed371e6" width="1" height="1" alt=""/>&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;<a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/price-cannibalisation-effect-a09f4ed371e6">Price cannibalisation effect</a> was originally published in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions">Clean Energy for Billions</a> on Medium, where people are continuing the conversation by highlighting and responding to this story.&lt;/p&gt;</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part II: The Incompleteness of LCoE</title><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-ii-the-incompleteness-of-lcoe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part II: The Incompleteness of LCoE"/><published>2025-04-18T07:30:37+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-18T07:30:37+00:00</updated><id>https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-ii-the-incompleteness-of-lcoe</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-ii-the-incompleteness-of-lcoe/"><![CDATA[<h3>Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part II: The Incompleteness of LCOE</h3> <h4>Renewables are much cheaper than fossil fuels — or are they?</h4> <blockquote>This <strong>five-part</strong> series dives deep into the economics of electricity markets and the role that markets can and must play in the decarbonisation journey. But in reality, do they? And what can be done about it?</blockquote> <blockquote>In this second part, <strong>The incompleteness of LCOE, </strong>let’s dissect the elements comprising the cost-side of the economics of a renewable energy project. I will highlight the misconceptions behind with the statement that “renewables are much cheaper than fossil fuels!”</blockquote> <blockquote>Read previous parts: <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-1-designed-for-the-past-495df82eb04a">Part I</a></blockquote> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*__op4i4hQ5Kzx8Uy"/><figcaption>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@angarav?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral">Antonio Garcia</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral">Unsplash</a></figcaption></figure> <p>Let’s dive into the economics of renewable energy projects by first looking at the expenses side of the analysis in this Part, followed by the revenue side of the picture in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-3-an-elephant-called-risk-2b7b37b4df7e">Part III</a>.</p> <p>To kick things off, let me introduce a popular metric called <em>Levelized Cost of Electricity (LCOE)</em>, which is often touted as a key indicator of the success story of clean energy transition. LCOE has been the metric of choice when it comes to comparing various electricity generation technologies for decades now.</p> <p>Stated simply, it is the <em>cost (including the cost of capital) in $/MWh of producing one unit of energy (MWh) from a generator, averaged over its operational lifetime</em>. <strong>Figure 1 </strong>below shows the evolution of LCOE for various technologies in the US over the last years. This cost evolution follow a similar trajectory in other countries around the world.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*35oCwvOFbspvwUoWPeg_4g.jpeg"/><figcaption>Figure 1: Historical evolution of Levelized Cost of Energy (LCOE) for various energy generation sources, built at utility scale. Data source: <a href="https://www.lazard.com/research-insights/levelized-cost-of-energyplus/">Lazard LCOE+</a>, June 2024.</figcaption></figure> <p>As can be seen, the LCOE for renewables, onshore wind and solar PV in particular, has fallen drastically over the years and has been below the fossil-fuel alternatives such as coal and gas around the world for nearly a decade now. And this is no small feat! Behind the lines on this chart, lies the incredible success story of how relatively new technologies have transitioned quickly from laboratories to large scale installations around the world, supported by a mature global supply chain of skills and components.</p> <p>It is therefore established that, from a cost perspective, renewables are already the preferred choice (and will increasingly become so as we start internalising the cost of carbon emissions. <em>More on that in a future article!</em>) for new electricity production projects.</p> <p><em>“All else being equal”</em>, this cost dynamic should bring a massive impetus for investors and banks to fund new renewable energy projects, right?</p> <p><em>Why then, one wonders, is that renewable energy projects face challenges?</em></p> <p>The answer lies in what LCOE is and what it isn’t.</p> <p>And that all else is NOT equal — far from it, actually!</p> <blockquote>While LCOE is a great metric to compare technologies and to track their technological maturity over the years, it is also incomplete and to put it bluntly, misleading, when it comes to investment decision-making.</blockquote> <h4>Bountiful, but far, far away</h4> <p>First, LCOE does not include geographical aspects of the costs, i.e., the cost of transporting electricity from the site of generation to consumption.</p> <p>This is not an issue for fossil fuel-based generators as they (i) typically have a smaller geographical footprint and (ii) are located optimally w.r.t. transportation networks, e.g., road-, rail-, and water-ways to transport the fuel. This layout often coincides with human settlements and demand centres, meaning that fossil fuel-based generators enjoy sweet synergies with the consumption from a geographical standpoint. This is besides the fact that the energy produced is largely <em>controllable</em> and <em>dispatch-able</em> (i.e., can be scheduled ahead of time and adapted to meet demand fluctuations) by adjusting the fuel input.</p> <p>Renewables, on the other hand, have a much larger geographical footprint and do not enjoy such synergies with existing infrastructure. To make matters worse, sites with high renewable production potential and large swathes of land (cheaply) available are often remote and located far away from the demand centres.</p> <p>In fact, one of the biggest roadblocks (and source of delays) for renewable projects is the <em>development process</em>. This refers to one of the steps before the power plant gets built, primarily concerned with identifying and securing the rights to the land (or seabed for offshore wind) and the necessary permits.</p> <p>Once that is in place, projects often require a massive build-up of expensive (and unpopular) power transmission lines and upgrades to the existing infrastructure to accommodate the changes in electricity flows across entire countries (or even continents, in extreme cases) to integrate large renewable energy projects to the electricity grid.</p> <p>In some cases (e.g., isolated small grids with weak connections to other grids), the additional infrastructure necessary to integrate renewables may be prohibitively expensive and stall the project after an initial feasibility study.</p> <blockquote>Generally speaking, even for large-scale, interconnected, strong grids, e.g., continental Europe and North America, such costs are not insignificant by any means.</blockquote> <blockquote>Critically, they increase as the grid becomes cleaner.</blockquote> <p>While a smaller share of weather-dependent renewables in the total generation mix may incur little to no grid integration costs (since other dispatch-able fossil-fuel based generators can provide the flexibility needed), an electricity grid dominated by such renewables faces high costs to maintain the supply-demand balance necessary for secure grid operation.</p> <p><strong>Figure 2</strong>, based on results from the <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0360544222018035">article</a> (<a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4028640">Open Access</a> available) from 2022, clearly illustrates such hidden costs.</p> <p><em>Full-system LCOE </em>refers to the LCOE value supplemented by the cost of balancing the grid (via the use of storage technologies, for instance) to meet the supply obligation mandated by the demand in the area and therefore, is an attempt to complete the picture painted by LCOE. The number 95% comes from the fact that 95% of the total system demand is assumed to be fulfilled by the technology in question whereas the remaining 5% is fulfilled by the cheapest producer in the system.</p> <p>It shows that considering the overall costs of enabling the consumption of a MWh of energy, <em>given the current paradigm that a consumer may demand that MWh at any time in that geographical region</em>, wind and solar PV no longer emerge as clear winners.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*ckdNChiQHjPFSyCol29cwQ.jpeg"/><figcaption>Figure 2: Full-system LCOE for various energy generation technologies compared between Texas and Germany, if 95% of the demand were fulfilled by the technology, with the remaining 5% fulfilled by an extremely cheap, fully-flexible generator. Data source: Robert Idel, “Levelized full system costs of electricity”, Energy, Volume 259:124905, 2022. (Note the discrepancy between the absolute LCOE values used here vs. those shown in Figure 1, particularly for natural gas, further illustrating the role of assumptions underlying the analysis.)</figcaption></figure> <p>Lastly, the study underscores that even with a 90% drop in the cost of storage, from a full-system LCOE perspective, wind and solar PV remain expensive compared to alternatives.</p> <h4>Cheap money or expensive money?</h4> <p>The second issue with LCOE, which is perhaps even more relevant from an investment decision point of view, is that it does not capture the temporal aspects of the costs.</p> <p>While the share of capital expenditure (aka CAPEX) in renewable energy projects is roughly 90–95% of the total project cost, it is only 60–70% in the case of fossil-fuel generators.</p> <blockquote>In the case of renewables, most of the large sum of money must be spent on fixed costs, e.g., land, equipment, and labour before even a single MWh of sellable electricity can be produced by the generator.</blockquote> <p>This is not the case for fossil fuel-based generators where operational expenditure (OPEX) forms a larger share of the total project cost, thereby spreading the cost component out over the lifetime of the project.</p> <p>Now this may not sound like a big deal, but recall that <em>cost of capital</em> is a key component of LCOE. In simple terms, cost of capital is defined as the expected rate of return that project developers require to attract funds to a particular project.</p> <p><em>It is, therefore, natural that a higher cost of capital would make a project more expensive.</em></p> <p>Moreover, the cost of capital is quite specific to the context of a project. Besides the prevailing macroeconomic factors such as interest rates, the technology underlying the project, geopolitical and regulatory environment, energy off-take agreements, etc. play a key role in determining it. Therefore, it varies dramatically across projects and is highly non-standardised. A recent <a href="https://www.irena.org/-/media/Files/IRENA/Agency/Publication/2023/May/IRENA_The_cost_of_financing_renewable_power_2023.pdf">report</a> by International Renewable Energy Agency (IRENA), focused on renewable energy financing, highlights that even for given a specific geography and a specific technology, cost of capital may vary significantly across projects. This stems partly from the fact that financial institutions often battle an expertise gap when assessing the risks associated with such non-standardised investments, and therefore, associate varied levels of risk premiums with them.</p> <p>Revisiting our sombre theme of <em>“all else NOT being equal”</em>, renewables face serious roadblocks when it comes to an increase in cost of capital specifically because of the timing of the costs incurred.</p> <p>Given that the high upfront costs are compensated over a long uncertain duration by the lower (almost zero) operating expenses and the expertise gap faced by financial institutions, renewable projects are qualified as much <em>riskier</em> investments compared to alternatives, as noted in the 2023 <a href="https://www.iea.org/commentaries/financial-headwinds-for-renewables-investors-what-s-the-way-forward">commentary</a> published by the International Energy Agency (IEA). Therefore, investors look for additional risk premiums while injecting funds into projects with renewables. The fact that the time for previously-discussed steps of permitting and grid connection often takes <a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/electricity-grids-and-secure-energy-transitions">years</a>, adds more uncertainty to such renewable energy projects, thereby further increasing the cost of capital.</p> <p>This makes the LCOE numbers, such as those shown in <strong>Figure 1</strong>, particularly misleading since they assume a common <em>discount rate</em> (as a proxy for cost of capital) across all technologies.</p> <h4>Fake it till you make it?</h4> <p>With such inadequacies inherent to the LCOE numbers, it is quite unfortunate that policy makers and their economic advisors alike, have regularly used (and still use) the downwards trending and seemingly favourable LCOE of renewables to justify the withdrawal of state support for renewables.</p> <p>While it is a sign of confidence on the technological progress we have made and economies of scale we have reached for renewables, it overlooks the crucial aspects of grid integration costs and the risk perception associated with the costs of such projects.</p> <p>It is, therefore, a welcome first step that recent academic works, such as <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2214629624004882?ref=pdf_download&amp;fr=RR-2&amp;rr=8fc25f593fa0eb54#bb0265">this</a>, are calling for a critical rethinking of this misunderstood metric to focus on the full-system costs. Focusing on extensive survey and analysis cost of capital across various geographies, works such as <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0140988320301237">this</a>, highlight the importance of understanding the disparities across geographies and involving financing costs as a key policy intervention measure for decarbonisation.</p> <blockquote>Unfortunately for the planet, while policy makers tend to measure the success of their clean energy policies by LCOE, banks and financial institutions do not care much about LCOE (nor for a rapidly warming planet, for that matter).</blockquote> <blockquote>They care about profitability: the expected returns and risk underlying it.</blockquote> <blockquote>To understand what this implies for clean energy transition, let’s shift our attention to the revenues and profitability side of the economics of renewable energy projects in the next part of this series “Part III: An elephant named Risk”.</blockquote> <p><a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-3-an-elephant-called-risk-2b7b37b4df7e">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part III: An elephant called Risk</a></p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=658c44470cce" width="1" height="1" alt=""/>&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;<a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-2-the-incompleteness-of-lcoe-658c44470cce">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part II: The Incompleteness of LCoE</a> was originally published in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions">Clean Energy for Billions</a> on Medium, where people are continuing the conversation by highlighting and responding to this story.&lt;/p&gt;</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part I: Designed for the past</title><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-i-designed-for-the-past/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part I: Designed for the past"/><published>2025-04-18T07:30:04+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-18T07:30:04+00:00</updated><id>https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-i-designed-for-the-past</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-i-designed-for-the-past/"><![CDATA[<h4>Designed in a bygone era when the script and actors were different, how do electricity markets fare in the current scene?</h4> <blockquote>Are electricity markets fit for the purpose of being a catalyst in accelerating the clean energy transition of our electricity system? The stakes couldn’t be higher — urgent and large-scale electrification of all energy use supported by a deep decarbonisation of the electricity sector is essential for climate change mitigation.</blockquote> <blockquote>This <strong>five-part</strong> series dives deep into the economics of electricity markets and the role that markets can and must play in the decarbonisation journey. But in reality, do they? And what can be done about it?</blockquote> <blockquote>This first part, <strong>Designed for the past </strong>sets the stage by recounting the history of electricity markets and highlights the inadequacy of current market framework in playing that crucial role in our decarbonisation journey.</blockquote> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*4ZXii2zZ09qstL8pYKoysg@2x.jpeg"/><figcaption>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@karsten_wuerth?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Karsten Würth</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/black-solar-panel-under-red-and-gray-clouds--tzkyLKPvL4?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Unsplash</a></figcaption></figure> <p>In July 2024, I stumbled upon an opinion piece by FT’s chief economics commentator and eminent financial journalist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Wolf">Martin Wolf</a>, headlined <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/b2b6fb7a-9477-4485-a9e3-435b5e9c987e"><em>Market forces are not enough to halt climate change</em></a>. Based on insights drawn from the latest policy briefs and data showing the recent global slowdown in renewable energy projects, Martin argues that, left to itself, “the energy market alone” will not fix the global failure to incentivise pro-climate growth.</p> <p>I was intrigued by the argument. Not because I disagreed with it (and not due to a lack of trying!), but because it ended on a somewhat hopeless note. Martin concludes that today’s geo-political fragmentation at the global stage and domestic populism within countries implies that we (read, <em>humanity</em>) lack the courage and conviction necessary to fix the tragic market failure behind the slowdown in clean energy transition.</p> <p>After having spent a large part of my PhD studies thinking about and proposing new market designs and pricing mechanisms in the electricity markets, specifically to accommodate the challenges that renewables bring, I couldn’t stop myself from reflecting on his remarks.</p> <p>There has to be a market-based fix to this global challenge, I wondered. A free market is, after all, the best coordination mechanism we have discovered so far to steer rational<em> </em>and self-interested<em> </em>actors towards building social utility. That competitive markets, guided by the proverbial <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Invisible_hand">invisible hand</a><em>, </em>are highly effective at organising economic activities such that truthful<em> </em>disclosure of preferences<em> </em>and costs<em>, </em>is not just evidence-backed but even mathematically provable.</p> <p>When it comes to electricity, the competitive wholesale markets that we know today (mature markets in Europe and North America, for example, and emerging ones such as in India and South America) have followed a series of <a href="https://www.wiley.com/en-dk/Fundamentals+of+Power+System+Economics%2C+2nd+Edition-p-9781119213246">liberalisation</a> and deregulation reforms of the sector, starting in the early 1990s.</p> <blockquote>If you’re interested to dive deeper, <a href="http://Green, 2008 provides a succinct account of this historical development anchored in a comparison between the European and North American electricity market design philosophies and how they can be expected to fare in the future context of low- carbon electricity systems">this article</a> provides succinct account of the historical development of electricity markets, anchored in a comparison between the European and North American market design philosophies and how they can be expected to fare in the future context of low-carbon electricity systems.</blockquote> <p>Our ongoing efforts to achieve the transition of energy systems towards renewable energy sources rely heavily on these market-based activities. However, it is now painfully clear that this transition is not occurring at the scale and pace necessary to reach our climate change mitigation targets.</p> <blockquote>If you’re interested in a reality check on climate change, and specifically it’s compatibility with the recent massive growth in AI, you are welcome to read my recently-published write-up:</blockquote> <p><a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/climate-change-and-an-ai-hooked-society-a-compatibility-check-d9a6a8d97cf6">Climate Change and an AI-hooked Society: A Compatibility Check</a></p> <h4>Cold response to a warming planet</h4> <p>Globally, commercial activities around investments in renewable energy projects are not showing encouraging signs.</p> <p>For instance, in Denmark, the undisputed global pioneer of wind energy, no bids at all were received for an auction of rights to develop 3 GW of offshore wind in adjoining North Sea. This was the first in a <a href="https://ens.dk/en/press/north-sea-offshore-wind-tendering-procedure-danish-energy-agency-has-not-received-any-bids">series of two auctions of 3 GW each</a>, with a potential for developers to overplant (i.e., exceed the installation goal) up to 10 GW.</p> <p>This auction series was deemed historic for two reasons, as envisioned by the auction organiser, the <a href="https://ens.dk/en/press/denmarks-largest-tendering-procedure-offshore-wind-power-launched">Danish Energy Agency</a>. First, due to the fact that the total planned installed capacity exceeded the current average electricity demand of the entire country by a long shot. Second, it was intended to open up avenues for electrification of hard-to-abate sectors via Power-to-X, thus significantly boosting the green hydrogen economy in Europe.</p> <p>While the fate met by this auction call was not surprising to many of us who are active in the Danish energy landscape, it undoubtedly (<em>and thankfully!</em>) drew attention to a few fundamental questions on the viability of our current approaches to stimulate investment in clean energy which must be addressed urgently. <em>(More details on that in an upcoming post!)</em></p> <p>Beyond Denmark, recent geopolitical developments have brewed a perfect maelstrom, caused by the pressure in global supply chains and growing uncertainty perceived by the global financial systems, which hinders renewable energy projects from seeing the light of the day.</p> <blockquote>In fact, in April 2025, the US Department of Interior issued an immediate <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/3e444c3a-b0ab-4062-8510-1e6a40411551">stop order</a> to Equinor to halt work on an <em>already-approved, under-construction </em>810 MW offshore wind project — a project in which Equinor has already spent $2bn and was expecting to start producing power as early as 2027!</blockquote> <blockquote>Thankfully, the stop work order was lifted later in May 2025 after <a href="https://www.equinor.com/news/20250519-empire-wind-project-resumes-construction">extensive dialogue</a> and construction work has resumed. But not without sending damaging ripples of uncertainty and anxiety across the energy supply chain!</blockquote> <p>Such a cold (and short-sighted) response to a rapidly warming planet brings me to this article series, which above all, is an attempt to reconcile the dilemma brewing in my head over the last several months.</p> <p><em>It is clear to me that while we have conquered the technological barriers to clean, zero-carbon energy for all, we are losing the battle against economics and geo-politics of the energy transition.</em></p> <p>And this is a battle we cannot afford to lose — because electricity generation is by far the easiest<strong> </strong>and most mature<strong> </strong>decarbonisation tool we have at our disposal to reduce our carbon emissions as a society.</p> <p>Therefore, <em>deeper</em><strong> </strong><em>electrification</em> of all energy usages coupled with <em>rapid decarbonisation</em> of the electricity system is crucial to ensure the continued prosperity of our future generations!</p> <p>While I strongly believe that efficient market-based activities are critical to delivery of clean energy to consumers, the more I reflect on the current state of energy markets and on the long-run investment signals generated by them, I conclude that our energy markets are clearly not fit for purpose.<em> </em>The purpose of being a catalyst in enabling the rapid and urgent large-scale transition to cleaner sources of electricity.</p> <p>And this is not surprising.</p> <blockquote>Designed for a former era of fossil fuels when fuel costs governed energy prices, cracks in the foundational structures of the market design start showing up in the new paradigm dominated by zero fuel cost (and zero opportunity cost) weather-dependent, renewable energy, such as wind and solar photovoltaics (PV).</blockquote> <blockquote><strong><em>So, what can and must be done about them?</em></strong></blockquote> <h4>Is the price wrong?</h4> <p>One of the works Martin cites in his article is Brett Christophers’ recently-published book, <a href="https://www.versobooks.com/products/3069-the-price-is-wrong"><em>The Price is Wrong: Why Capitalism Won’t Save the Planet</em></a><em>.</em></p> <p>The book meticulously crafts a rather provocative narrative of how the market-based approach <em>has not </em>and<em> will not</em> lead to reaching climate change mitigation targets, given the technological, regulatory, and financial milieu the electricity system operates in.</p> <figure><img alt="Cover page of the book, Is the Price Wrong by Brett Christophers" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/287/0*DHTxPoXxowwh_TZ2"/><figcaption>The Price is Wrong by Brett Christophers (Image source: <a href="https://www.versobooks.com/products/3069-the-price-is-wrong">Verso Books</a>)</figcaption></figure> <p>Brett’s thesis is a demonstration, via a rather sophisticated yet solid chain of arguments that — <em>without financial support from governments, renewables have not and will not get built at scale</em>.</p> <p>In fact, he goes as far as saying that only the state has the financial and logistical capabilities to deliver the trillions of dollars of investment annually needed in wind and solar projects to prevent a catastrophic climate outcome for the planet.</p> <p>Notwithstanding the clear leftist inclination of the work, I wholeheartedly recommend the book to anyone seeking to understand the nitty-gritty of the geopolitics stifling the global clean energy transition.</p> <p>Personally, the book left a lasting impression on me. In particular, due to the breadth of sources Brett relies upon to drive across the point that current electricity markets are hindering the clean energy transition.</p> <blockquote><em>What emerges from the narrative is that the failure of markets is so stark and shocking that the very mechanisms we have devised to competitively and efficiently enable the transaction of large volumes of energy are becoming the irrelevant middle person in the transaction between producers and consumers.</em></blockquote> <p>And this is clearly evident from the increasing share of long-term, fixed-price backed Power Purchase Agreements (PPAs) becoming the cornerstone of successful renewable energy projects.</p> <p>Without the revenue stability guarantee provided by such PPAs, investors and banks, having well-meaning intentions to provide the needed financial backing for these large-scale capital-intensive projects, develop cold feet.</p> <p>To understand why this happens, one needs to dive into the economics of such renewable energy projects.</p> <p>After all, it is the outcome of economic assessments made by investors and banks that ultimately decides whether a project gets built successfully and starts producing clean energy.</p> <blockquote>First, let’s take a look at the expenses side of this economic picture in the next part in this series “Part II: The incompleteness of LCOE”.</blockquote> <p><a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-2-the-incompleteness-of-lcoe-658c44470cce">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part II: The Incompleteness of LCoE</a></p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=495df82eb04a" width="1" height="1" alt=""/>&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;<a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/are-electricity-markets-fit-for-purpose-part-1-designed-for-the-past-495df82eb04a">Are electricity markets fit for purpose? Part I: Designed for the past</a> was originally published in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions">Clean Energy for Billions</a> on Medium, where people are continuing the conversation by highlighting and responding to this story.&lt;/p&gt;</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Climate Change and AI-hooked Society: A Compatibility Check</title><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/climate-change-and-ai-hooked-society-a-compatibility-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate Change and AI-hooked Society: A Compatibility Check"/><published>2025-04-12T12:52:15+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-12T12:52:15+00:00</updated><id>https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/climate-change-and-ai-hooked-society-a-compatibility-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2025/climate-change-and-ai-hooked-society-a-compatibility-check/"><![CDATA[<h3>Climate change and AI-hooked society: A compatibility check</h3> <h4>Recent AI growth is on a collision course with its carbon footprint and climate cost — a discourse that’s been simmering in the last couple of years is becoming mainstream. This week IEA published a special report on AI and its energy use, and how it could shape the future of our energy systems and climate change, by extension. This article contextualises the report in the current geopolitical and financial environment, given the woes of our rapidly warming planet.</h4> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*O2Az9qQ76ZVa78_J72XBxA.jpeg"/><figcaption>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@markuswinkler?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Markus Winkler</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/scrabble-tiles-spelling-climate-on-a-wooden-surface-azOswAoYu_0?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Unsplash</a></figcaption></figure> <p>Earlier this week, International Energy Agency (IEA) released a special report titled, <a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/energy-and-ai"><em>Energy and AI</em></a><em>, </em>addressing the recent rapid growth the Artificial Intelligence (AI) sector from an energy use lens.</p> <p>The recent mass adoption of Generative AI has put immense pressure on the electricity grid due to the increasing energy consumption by data centers training models and providing services to hundreds of millions of users worldwide. In absolute terms, currently, data centers consume roughly 1.5% of electricity globally and it is one of the fastest growing electricity demands, expected to double by 2030. Moreover, the challenges often arise when one considers <em>where</em> this electricity demand comes from (concentrated geographical pockets near cities) and <em>when</em> it is expected to be fulfilled (often, the mismatch between renewable generation and data center consumption leads to <em>green washing</em> via clean energy certificates).</p> <p>In fact, the spatio-temporal pressure exerted on the electricity grid by this rapidly-increasing demand is often under-estimated and unfortunately, misrepresented in <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/johnwerner/2024/05/03/sam-altman-on-climate-and-entrepreneurship/">popular media</a> by interested parties.</p> <p>The narrative weaved is not only that current (and future) AI sector’s energy consumption is dwarfed by other sectors, but also that AI’s widespread, cross-sectoral adoption will empower experts to come up with solutions that will solve climate change altogether in the future, thus rendering such concerns moot.</p> <p>However, the fact is that besides the power-hungry data centers and their demand for cooling, the global supply chain of chip manufacturing and assembly is also a highly energy-intensive, precise manufacturing process. This is crucial because often chip manufacturing occurs in Asian tech hubs such as China, Taiwan, Japan, and South Korea, where fossil-fuel based electricity generation, e.g., coal-fired power plants still dominate the energy mix and cater to these <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2021-04-08/the-chip-industry-has-a-problem-with-its-giant-carbon-footprint">growing</a> industrial demand.</p> <h4>Competing for natural resources, investment, and talent</h4> <p>Now, I am not someone who is skeptical of the massive (mostly positive) impact AI technologies will have on improving ordinary people’s lives and, therefore, I am not against growth in this sector. I believe in the transformative capabilities of this technology in enhancing human productivity and efficiency, being an early and curious adopter myself.</p> <p><strong>But, I am deeply troubled by this narrative.</strong></p> <p>Climate change is an immediate and existential threat, with sharply escalating cost of inaction over time. Dealing with this challenge demands intense focus, bold decisions, and steadfast commitment from leaders and decision-makers. Each year that goes where actions fall short of what’s required, we are stacking up the future societal cost of climate change on humanity, both in terms of lives lost and livelihoods impacted.</p> <p>Therefore, the fact that such a narrative around AI diverts crucial resources away from climate tech, i.e., innovations helping fight climate change, and towards AI-focused innovations is extremely concerning to me.</p> <p>Recent articles, such as <a href="https://www.investmentnews.com/industry-news/climate-tech-funding-slumps-as-investors-prioritize-ai/259120#:~:text=The%20rise%20of%20artificial%20intelligence,%2420%20billion%20to%20%2432%20billion.">this</a> and <a href="https://www.pwc.com/gx/en/issues/esg/climate-tech-investment-adaptation-ai.html">this</a>, lament the slowdown in funding for climate tech sector while investor funding for AI soars. In fact, 2024 witnessed a 40% year-on-year decline in equity financing for climate tech after witnessing several years of growth, while AI (primarily, generative AI) exploded by 80% year-on-year.</p> <p>This trend can only be expected to continue in the near-term, as the world gears up for a century-defining global AI arms race. At the time of writing this article, unfortunately, the world order is being rejigged, uncertainty remains high for financial markets, and a global turmoil seemingly looms around the corner.</p> <p>I acknowledge that rationality demands decision-makers to focus on building adaptation and resilience against the short-term geopolitical threats. And that is understandable, but it must not replace the focus on actions to mitigate the threat that climate change poses.</p> <p>Moreover, the cost of this shifting focus from humanity-saving climate tech towards <em>Studio Ghibli </em>style rendering of our photos, however joy-giving, appears nothing short of epic stupidity beyond comprehension to me.</p> <p>Besides money, it diverts some of the smartest human beings on the planet towards AI, away from working to find solutions to the most pressing challenge of our lifetime, i.e., climate change. And I must admit, if one is talented, it is tempting to ride this new wave of AI technology and bask in the hype that it enjoys.</p> <p>However, the world needs all the resources it can muster right now to focus on developing solutions that urgently upscale our efforts to avoid catastrophic and irreversible climate change — to safeguard our survival.</p> <p>And the time is running out!</p> <h4>Woes of a warming planet</h4> <p>Year after year, the wording in United Nations Environment Programme’s annually-published report focusing on <em>Emissions Gap </em>(a metric tracking the discrepancy between what nations have “pledged to do” vs. “what needs to be done”) keeps getting grimmer.</p> <p><strong>Keep in mind that these are still pledges made and not actions completed!</strong></p> <p>Their <a href="https://www.unep.org/resources/emissions-gap-report-2024">latest report</a> shows that on a global level we are regressing in our efforts to reduce carbon emissions. And that the time lost in geopolitical and nationalistic power games has severe implications for the carbon budget available for the remainder of this century to prevent catastrophic climate change.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*bjZItJyVaq4Uaf-Uy1cxQQ.png"/><figcaption>Figure 1: Projections of Global Mean Surface Temperature (GMST) under the pledge-based various scenarios (Source: <a href="https://www.unep.org/resources/emissions-gap-report-2024">UNEP report</a>) Note the top row refers to the current policies running unaltered, whereas the other rows refer to the various scenarios for Nationally Determined Contributions (NDCs) pledged by the countries. The probabilities indicate the likelihood of reaching a range of GMST under a given actions (or pledges) scenario by year 2100.</figcaption></figure> <p>In fact, as evident from Figure 1, the 1.5 C warming cap (over pre-industrial levels) that governments signed up for in the Paris Agreement in 2015 is no longer feasible. Current pledges imply that the temperature would still rise between 2.6 and 2.8 C by 2100, which spells horrifying outcomes for millions of people and for a number of biological ecosystems.</p> <blockquote>“The world has currently warmed by about 1.3 C already”, Gloria Dickie reports sombrely in <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/environment/climate-set-warm-by-31-c-without-greater-action-un-report-warns-2024-10-24/">Reuters</a>.</blockquote> <p>Unfortunately and surprisingly (even for climate experts), 2024 was the first year where the <strong>Global Mean Surface Temperature (GMST)</strong> crossed the “1.5 C above the pre-industrial level” threshold. The verdict is unclear whether this was just an anomaly or the beginning of a trend (since 2023 also reported higher than normal).</p> <p>A recent scientific <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adq7280">article</a> (available <a href="https://epic.awi.de/id/eprint/59831/1/adq7280_Merged_AcceptedVersion_v20241206.pdf">Open Access</a>) uses satellite data from NASA and climate reanalysis data from ECMWF to conclude that these observations can be largely explained by the reduction in low-level clouds across the planet, which help cooling the planet by increasing the reflectivity of the atmosphere to solar radiation (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_albedo">cloud albedo</a>). That the reduction in low-level clouds is linked to the increasing GMST suggests that this anomaly may, in fact, be the beginning of a trend (possibly an addition to the list of so-called global climatic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tipping_points_in_the_climate_system"><em>tipping points</em></a>) and not just an anomaly is quite worrisome.</p> <p>Not only this, recent academic works, such as <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/epdf/10.1126/sciadv.1601666">this</a> and <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-023-39810-w">this</a>, has unfortunately, been pointing to another tipping point being reached sooner than estimated. This refers to the slowing down (and possibly eventual collapse) of the <strong>Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation </strong>(AMOC) current which is one of the crucial elements of the circulation system of our planet. A collapse of the AMOC current brings devastating news for Europe and has severe climatic ramifications on the entire world.</p> <blockquote>While climate scientists debate the “<em>when” </em>of this (partial or total) collapse, there is broad consensus that it is not a question of “<em>if”, </em>unless large-scale and urgent actions on climate change mitigation are taken right now!</blockquote> <p>And it deeply worries me to write that, one cannot reasonably rule out this collapse from happening within our lifetime, around the 2050s, if we continue pumping CO2 into our atmosphere business-as-usual. In fact, considering the severe impact the collapse of AMOC could have in the Nordic region (see Figure 2, below), climate scientists from around the world wrote an <a href="https://en.vedur.is/media/ads_in_header/AMOC-letter_Final.pdf">Open Letter to the Nordic Council of Ministers</a> last October, highlighting how our previous estimates of the severity of this slowdown might be <em>biased</em> and <em>incorrect</em> and that the risk is likely higher than originally thought.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*PJ6xo-U7RGQv09SxFcK_jA.png"/><figcaption>Figure 2: Annual mean temperature change in a future CO2 doubling scenario in which the AMOC has fully collapsed. The so-called ‘cold blob’ in Northern Atlantic is likely to bring unprecedented extreme cold weather to the Nordic countries threatening the viability of agriculture in Northwestern Europe, while leading to massive shifts in rainfall and temperature patterns and increased risk of weather anomalies in the rest of the world. Sources: <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.1601666">Science Advances</a>, <a href="https://en.vedur.is/media/ads_in_header/AMOC-letter_Final.pdf">Open Letter</a></figcaption></figure> <h4>From a lopsided nexus to symbiotic partnership</h4> <p>So where does this lead us?</p> <p>The IEA <a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/energy-and-ai">report</a> on <em>Energy and AI</em> that I referred to earlier, concludes that the AI and energy sectors are more intertwined than ever, that they are in a <em>nexus</em> that is expected to bear fruit for the world. While the authors express their concerns about the uncertainties that lie ahead, specifically around <em>what energy generation sources fuel this growth in AI demand for electricity</em>, their overall outlook remains neutral to positive. This stems from the advances in energy efficiency of AI models, such as <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.19437"><em>DeepSeek</em></a><em>, </em>as well as the <em>voluntary</em> interest in green Power Purchase Agreements (PPAs) and nuclear energy shown by tech giants, such as Apple and Google.</p> <p>I wish I could fully share their optimism. If history teaches us anything about such a cocktail of <em>fast-paced progress coupled with intense industry lobbying efforts to secure profits</em>, it is to not be complacent about the long-term impacts they bring.</p> <p><em>I can’t help but recognise parallels to the oil and gas industry from half a century ago, when the research and discourse on global warming was</em><a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/exxon-knew-about-climate-change-almost-40-years-ago/"><em> deliberately and meticulously suppressed</em></a><em> and the world was misled by oil and gas giants towards climate change denial, while they kept raking in profits.</em></p> <p>We, as a society, must not fall for a similar trap again, because frankly, we cannot afford to. <strong>Our survival depends on it.</strong></p> <p>The climate impacts of AI must, therefore, neither be underestimated nor be overshadowed by the narrative of “<em>AI is for societal good”</em>, especially in the most crucial decade for humanity from a climate change mitigation perspective.</p> <p>I believe that proactive policy and regulation needs to step up to make AI technology not only <strong>compatible with </strong>but also <strong>answerable for</strong> addressing the global challenge of climate change.</p> <p>Policy-makers around the world must force the large corporate beneficiaries of the AI boom to internalise the negative externality of their undertakings on the global climate into their business models. And that it must be paid for, in full, by them. Not via green washing or purchasing carbon credits or renewable certificates, but by enforcing requirements such as hourly-matching of data center consumption with renewable production, mandated funding of clean energy project development and/or innovation, etc.</p> <p>And we are seeing some encouraging <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/04/apple-ramps-up-investment-in-clean-energy-and-water-around-the-world/">progress</a>, but so far it has been voluntary and concentrated in a few geographies. As progress in AI becomes global and countries around the world build their own AI capabilities aggressively, it is extremely important for regulation to step up. Our AI-hooked advanced society in the 21st century must be built on principles of sustainability and climate change mitigation.</p> <p>Thankfully, this detailed 300-page report by IEA brings more attention to this important and timely issue, covering it in depth and providing trends and insights to policy makers and relevant subject matter experts.</p> <p>I hope that the ensuing dialogue is solution-focused and not one built around shirking and deferring responsibility.</p> <p><em>It’s time to start turning the current lopsided relationship, where AI benefits more from the energy sector towards a symbiotic cooperation between the two sectors towards solving the </em><a href="https://press.un.org/en/2021/sc14445.doc.htm"><em>greatest threat humanity</em></a><em> has ever faced — Climate Change.</em></p> <p><em>Thank you for reading! I would love to hear your thoughts and insights on this topic.</em></p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=d9a6a8d97cf6" width="1" height="1" alt=""/>&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;<a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions/climate-change-and-an-ai-hooked-society-a-compatibility-check-d9a6a8d97cf6">Climate Change and AI-hooked Society: A Compatibility Check</a> was originally published in <a href="https://medium.com/clean-energy-for-billions">Clean Energy for Billions</a> on Medium, where people are continuing the conversation by highlighting and responding to this story.&lt;/p&gt;</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Ascent</title><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2024/ascent/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ascent"/><published>2024-05-05T17:54:10+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-05T17:54:10+00:00</updated><id>https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2024/ascent</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2024/ascent/"><![CDATA[<figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*5TSD9L97xNp6TM_dbkwgsA.jpeg"/><figcaption>Matterhorn, CH (16.07.2022)</figcaption></figure> <p>It’s not only the mountains, with<br/>snowy peaks and treacherous falls,<br/>an ascent from a chaotic mind — <br/>just as challenging for a human.<br/>Sizing up a hill from it’s foot,<br/>craning one’s neck upwards,<br/>using gaze as a measuring stick — <br/>equally nerve-wracking<br/>as pulling oneself out of bed,<br/>on a dark morning, with<br/>not much to look forward to.</p> <p>Yet, it’s the first steps up<br/>that are the most crushing of all,<br/>first activity in the morning — <br/>the most daunting to conquer.<br/>Like a solo hiker up the mountain,<br/>a solo crusader of one’s own mind<br/>is bound to find friendly fellows,<br/>each scaling their own mountain<br/>inside their own heads, built<br/>as their worldviews and realities collide,<br/>the faults in their own footing manifest<br/>as insurmountable peaks all around.</p> <p>Up, together, is the only way out.</p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=c23b36ba0036" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Sun-blissed</title><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2024/sun-blissed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sun-blissed"/><published>2024-02-18T09:04:30+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-18T09:04:30+00:00</updated><id>https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2024/sun-blissed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2024/sun-blissed/"><![CDATA[<figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*kHwLXFbjf1OKeee1cQICVQ.jpeg"/></figure> <p>Unformed thoughts<br/>stream slowly from the soul<br/>as one looks down<br/>a promenade brought to life — <br/>the shimmer of blue water;<br/>the smiles worn by strangers;<br/>a flock of animated seagulls,<br/>sharing morsels strewn across;<br/>a group of spirited students,<br/>collaborating over homework.</p> <p>Flags of many kinds on sturdy poles,<br/>fluttered by the breeze’s gentle caress;<br/>glares from the facades and windows<br/>of shiny towers &amp; brick townhouses<br/>across the water on the other side — <br/>splattered on over the blue,<br/>broken into a million pieces;<br/>the shadows of people and poles,<br/>stretched long and thin by the<br/>oblique light from the horizon.</p> <p>Walkway paved by cobblestone tiles,<br/>held together by the green moss<br/>peeking out around the edges — <br/>breathing for the first time, perhaps,<br/>after the winter’s brutal blow;<br/>tiny bits of many conversations<br/>picked up from people walking by — <br/>a story with a multitude of characters,<br/>all strangers walking under the sun,<br/>held together by the season’s first warm rays.</p> <p>Sun-blissed and alive — winter’s on its way out.</p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=b2c69d2d2d32" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Hopes &amp;amp; Dreams</title><link href="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2024/hopes-dreams/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hopes &amp;amp; Dreams"/><published>2024-01-16T23:21:09+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-16T23:21:09+00:00</updated><id>https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2024/hopes--dreams</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anubhavratha.github.io/blog/2024/hopes-dreams/"><![CDATA[<figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*VjAfRP7_bF-ZNGnm"/><figcaption>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@carsive?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral">Ahmed Hasan</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral">Unsplash</a></figcaption></figure> <p>Incessant squirms of pain — a body, twisted unnaturally. <br/>A few rays of hope, plenty for the soul to cope.<br/>And yet unfelt energy gently guides the daily flow.</p> <p>Tapestry of distasteful thoughts — a mind, trapped firmly.<br/>A few strings of dreams, plenty to drown out the screams.<br/>And yet undiscovered joy pierces its way through.</p> <p>They will materialize — hopes &amp; dreams.</p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=fb2fd7de006b" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>